so the question that the Buddhist
teaching the entire Buddhist teaching is
is really addressing
is the question of what leads to
suffering and what leads to non-sufferers
non-sufferers
welfare and happiness
basically as opposed to what leads to
longlasting harm and
suffering that's at least that's how One
S of puts
it and it's so it's not this really
abstruse complex philosophical question
it's apparently basic question but if
you don't know the answer for yourself
to that
question then there's kind of no point
in asking anything else or anything else
you're asking or doing should really be
for the sake of gaining that
understanding for yourself
first that's also the that's also pretty
much the definition of Right View having
knowledge internal internal Clarity and
knowledge for yourself in regards to
what leads to suffering and what leads
to
non-sufferers to to gain that knowledge
for myself and so it's
myself and so it's
um it's kind of unpleasant to to admit
that and feel the weight of that
responsibility so like if you do admit
that then if you if you recognize that
you don't know or that your knowledge is
at least severely limited um or
incomplete in regard to what what leads
to longlasting welfare and happiness
versus what leads to long-term harm and
suffering and you recognize there is a
possibility of of knowing G gaining that
right view then so how should you what can you
view then so how should you what can you
do to start gaining this start to start
getting that that right Clarity and
understanding how should you think and
how should you act I don't want to just
give a list like there are specific
things um and I'm going to come to them
in a minute that things that you can do
like behaviors actions but what
ultimately really leads to uh to to
longlasting welfare and happiness and to
the end of suffering is is knowing that
the that that for yourself so not having
to depend on somebody to tell you what
specific things to
do and actually that's also how you can
start to understand your non
understanding which is which is um which
is an important thing to do like you can
think think about the fact that you
don't what does it mean that I don't
know for myself what leads
to end of suffering or how to put an end
to suffering you can basically see the
limit to your own
knowledge wherever there is anxiety or
wherever there's possibility for like
anxiety or fear um or this kind of deep
doubt and uncertainty about the nature
of things to be
there be and that's and that's um
already sort of revealing the the basic
nature or structure of of things that
um that is the reason for that anxiety
or the reason for that anxiety is lack
of understanding in regard to that
nature of things um and so like I'm
saying that because
um that's a way of basically already
directly for yourself without referring
to what somebody else has told you you
can recognize ize okay I don't know for
myself what leads to the end of of
suffering and I know that I don't know
because I get anxious and because I'm
afraid um and now okay why am I anxious
or what makes me anxious and Afraid you
can recognize that like really
fundamentally the reason for that for
any kind of anxiety or fear is um you
can see that your possibility of
managing your
circumstances or for your life in ways
that um that that that make you happy
um that that that make you happy
basically or that maintain your
well-being maintain your happiness or
that avoid suffering is itself basically
contained within certain things that you
have no possibility of controlling or
managing so and that's why there's
anxiety so like you might be able today
to you know go to work to get it you
know have um maintain your living
maintain your family
uh get enough food and so on but all of
those things are only possible because
your body is healthy because things are
set up in a certain way that is working
this there's peace in your in your in
your country hopefully all of those
things can
change and are changing for
somebody constantly at at any time at
any moment somebody is losing things on
a very fundamental level that means
they're losing even the possibility of
you know doing whatever they can to
maintain their own their own happiness
and avoid suffering
suffering
um and ultimately like for everybody no
matter how fortunate their circumstances
happen to be in their lives that applies
because no matter what you do your life
is is is going to end in kind of a dead
end or literally a dead end the the
ending of
death which really undermines if you
think about it anything that you can do
on a particular level um to to maintain
well-being or to avoid
suffering I was trying to think of like
an analogy for this whole sort of
situation the best one I could come up
with was um that it's a bit like
you're being held confined in a in a in
a prison cell that's um that's with a
guard a prison guard in charge of it
and and so you can ask the guard to give
you things in your prison cell like give
me food give you things to to do give
you whatever give you whatever you might
want to ask him
for um and and he if he's in a good mood
if he's uh well disposed towards you he
might he gives them to you basically so
the the guard um is your means of
accessing everything that you have in
this PR prison s
um but that's up to the guard whether he
gives them to you or not and ultimately
he's the one holding you in that prison
cell and he's not holding there holding
you there with uh with your uh with your
happiness in mind he's holding there
he's as a prison guard to keep you
prisoner he doesn't have your best
interests at heart so what this
basically represents is like the the
prison cell is kind of your entire life
your situation and um with the guard
there representing basically your body
and senses that are kind of your means
of accessing anything in particular or
doing anything in particular in your
life or any particular Pleasures um that
you might get you can only get them on
account of of your body and your senses
which as long as they're working and as
long as they're kind of treating you
well it it goes okay but um what people
what it's what you forget or it's
Pleasant to to not to not think about is
the fact that you're very um yeah your
very ability to access anything in
particular that might make you happy um
or to avoid anything that might make you
suffer has to go through that body so
it's like it's again like in the in that
analogy the guard at any moment it's up
to him at any moment he might just not
show up he might just he might decide to
to not give you the thing that you ask
for or he might decide to throw uh to
throw horrible things to you inside the
prison still instead of pleasant things
so even if he's nice to you most of the
time um if somebody is very lucky it's
it's still ultimately um not a good not
a good situation and it's not good to
depend on that um on that guard and
depend on on the things in the prison
cell for your long-term welfare and
happiness that's really where the
relevance of U virtue and sense
restraints come in in regard to even
being able to
um to see what's for your long-term
welfare and
happiness um and we talk a lot about
that obviously but it's not just this um
this random prerequisite virtue and
sense restraint so that you can get the
right View it's very directly relevant
to this question of what's for your
longlasting welfare and happiness happiness
um
and and that should be if you've been
thinking about about things in the in the way
about about things in the in the way
that I've just outlined it should
already start to make sense why
developing virtue for
example um would be more along the lines
of what would be for your welfare and
happiness rather than depending on
specific things in your life that you
hold dear or that bring you
Joy and that's because
while um circumstances changing or uh can
um circumstances changing or uh can
basically can take away or
can can destroy literally anything
in particular that you can think of in
your life that um that you would hold
dear they can't that virtue is not
something that can be just taken away in
that sense if it's being developed
properly along the right lines the
that's that aggregate of virtue
um is something that is basically more
uh Worthy to uh to develop and to depend
on than things like your body or
anything that depends on your body so I
what I mean by developing the aggregate
of virtue as well it's not just it it
would start obviously by taking on the
basic that the precepts so like
practicing practicing at least the five
precepts and ideally celibacy is the
third but also then on top of that it
means having um having an attitude of
just trying to avoid any fault in your
in in your actions so avoiding any
intentions actions that are rooted in
greed aversion delusion distraction
impatience jealousy we all kind of know
the things that shouldn't be done and
that so you shouldn't so what you know
shouldn't be done you don't do it when
it's rooted in a in an UNH wholesome
intention and so um prioritizing this
generally in your life prioritizing the
development of that virtue every day and
working on that and having that as as
something that is that is really your
priority as opposed to any other
particular goal that you might be trying
to achieve that's already even if you're
not specifically thinking about it and
even if you're not specifically aiming
to practice the Buddhist teaching that's
already going to um train your mind to
be more content to have more strength to
have more uh
resilience and and you can see why that
is because it's
because it's
like whatever might happen on a
particular level like even if um even if
you lose your health or you lose um
particular things that can't that can't
remove your virtue it can't U make you
be dis start to be dishonest or start to
to act out of ill will and so on and
that's kind of an important thing to
recognize even in itself because even if
you follow that reflection through to
its conclusion that's already showing
you um something important which is
really like the line between where your
responsibility begins and where it ends
so like even if even if your own family
is
attacked that doesn't make you and
doesn't justify you than attacking
somebody else that's a completely
different thing
thing
um and just as you you can't guarantee
no matter what you do you can't
guarantee that your body will stay
healthy but even ill health can't can't
make you unver virtuous if you've been
training your mind and training your
behavior in that aggregate of virtue so
basically that's why like you can see
virtue is is more worthy to um to depend
on than than your
body and that's also why why it's like
um as the suas put it it's a source of
blameless Joy when when that aggregate
of virtue is developed correctly it's
um like they they give that simile of a
king who has defeated his enemies and he
sees no danger from any direction
because he sees somebody who's developed
this aggregate of virtue would see and
know that nothing that can happen can
take can take away that good of virtue
it's just it's it's there it's been
developed nothing can make them act out
of act out of ill will act out of
greed
um and that's also actually by the way
why it's um why that that that is pretty
much developing the um composure of the
mind so it's a composure in the sense of
literally like something that
contains anything that might happen or
change on a particular level um day to
day so um so whatever might might happen
will the mind will will become kind of
immovable in it and that's literally
because it has been developed along this
lines of of recognizing its own
responsibility in regards to other
things that that other people might do
or that or that might change on a on a
on a particular level and so so yeah
it's containing you in the face of all
the disturbance that might that happens
in in your body in your life in in
everything else that's also why um that
that develops the the capacity for your
mind to be able to start contemplating
and recognizing the nature of things um
that that kind of deep rooted an anxiety
that I mentioned earlier and what that
what that is rooted in it um that
basically means
when you then start to contemplate the
nature of impermanence and and change in
general and things that would make you
deeply anxious and afraid it means that
you're able to do so without uh just
kind of falling apart and needing to
shut your eyes to it and resort to some
sensual pleasure or something to forget
about it you have something to fall back
on to resort to to contain you I mean if
you think about that simile that I
mentioned uh that I mentioned earlier
about this uh the guard and the prison
cell sensuality basically means um
taking the the particular things that
you can get through the guard as your as
a source of of Happiness basically so
you can see immediately how that is
completely the opposite to um to
anything that would allow you to um to
recognize the nature of that situation
for what it is because it's literally
just rooted in ignoring the situation
like you know quickly guard give me
something um give me something that I
can play with that I can look at that I
can enjoy that I can take pleasure
in it's basically just kind of fueling
your sense of of being in control of the
prison um like you think you're the king
of the
prison um just because you can keep asking the
um just because you can keep asking the
guard for something and he gives it to
you so it's like kind of um helping you
to ignore that fundamental lack of
ownership and lack of
control um so as long as you're keeping
doing that it's completely impossible to
actually recognize the situation for
what it
is um and it's also making you obviously
more and more dependent on those on the
guards it's putting you more and more um
under his command and under his control
the more you depend on the things that
he can give you the the the more that um
the more he has the capacity to hurt you
and and um and the more easily HT he can
hurt you and that's why he can he can
start torturing torturing you harming
you and and killing you as the body does
in the
end so that's why like nobody Who
develops the Right View can possibly um
maintain that valuing of sensuality
and um and it's also
why sensual pleasure really um from the
point of from that point of view of what
actually leads to long-term last
long-term welfare and happiness as
opposed to harm and suffering sensuality
is a source of of like blameworthy
happiness if you want to put it in that
way or really ultimate it's it's not
something pleasant it's not something
that is
um worthy to worth worthy to rely on or
worthy to engage in and and restraint on
the other
hand is actually um is is much more
pleasant from that point of view the the
that comp composed and contained mind
has the capacity to see things clearly
as it as they are I think there's a Sut
that says that as well then it's
possible to contemplate those same
thoughts that would
um that would make you very anxious or
afraid or that are are kind of pretect
in to where that deep bruised anxiety
is I start to contemplate them um
accurately which basically means
contemplating the nature of your
situation ACC accurately without turning
away from it without uh finding another
way to ignore it without um kind of uh
resorting to some um some method or
management thing to just cam your mind
down but just to to basically hold it there
but just to to basically hold it there
until you can start to
see the why the the reason for that
anxiety is not in the the the thing and
is not in the the way that things are
but is in your own kind of gratuitous
resistance or attitudes wrong attitudes
in regard to the way that that the
things are so and that really just comes
down to having an attitude of sense of
ownership and sense of control control
over things that you realize were never
yours to own were never in your control
and could never even be possible to own
or
control um and that's like and that's
when the mind would kind of let go of
that um let go of that anxiety and let
go of that resistance because it would
see how futile and useless it
is um like it's it makes no difference
to the situation anyway so it's it's um
and that's why it's that's why it's
really the cause of suffering but again
that's something that you can only
see if you have been if you've been
developing your mind along the right
lines if not it's like literally your
whole mindset is set against it is set
in maintaining the ignorance of it is
maintaining the impossibility of seeing
it